RYAN CELESLIE

314-363-2299 • ryan.celeslie@outlook.com • www.ryanceleslie.com • github.com/ryanceleslie • Cincinnati, Ohio

Summary

Software engineering leader with 20 years of experience and a decade in leadership, adhering to servant leadership to foster growth and innovation. Successful in strategic planning, technical strategy, and enterprise software engineering, while managing diverse, cross-discipline teams to maintain high standards and achieve software excellence.

Strengths



Leading teams of cross-discipline professionals, fostering growth, fulfillment, and technical excellence at a scale of 70+ employees.



Scrum Mindset

Regularly achieve a +95% on deliverables, showcasing a culture of ownership, accountability, and prioritizing customer feedback.



Strategic and Technical Planning

Instrumental in designing software systems, including microservices and domain decomposition.

Experience

Senior Director of Software Development

Cincinnati, OH

06/2022 - 02/2023

AssureCare

Championed the software engineering for a top pharmaceutical and clinical healthcare software provider, leading to a 25% improvement in software quality and a 65% decrease in post-launch defects for all products, as well as HL7 and FHIR compliance

- · Led the transition to Microservices for all products and features, ensuring seamless integration with legacy systems and 25% faster feature delivery compared to legacy software updates
- Spearheaded the implementation of microservice design decisions such as BFF Pattern and Eventual Consistency with the architecture team, enhancing code quality and system efficiency, leading to a 35% increase in velocity of strangled code
- Decreased the time-to-delivery 50% with stakeholder review and iteration, 65% reduction in defects by using Orthogonal Defect Classification (ODC) for bugs
- Increased successful team deliverables 90% using scrum and established high level developer support process to mitigate work that impacting commitments
- Reduced Azure costs 13% by utilizing Docker to eliminate need for development and QA cloud environments

Director of Software Development

Cincinnati, OH

Tide Cleaners at P&G

03/2020 - 05/2022

Directed the software technical strategy and oversaw the integration of digital solutions for a top-tier laundry and dry cleaning service provider, resulting in a 75% increase in software confidence

- Engineered a cutting-edge .NET Microservice platform leveraging REST APIs with DDD/CQRS architecture; embracing SOLID/Clean principles and Outbox Pattern to achieve Eventual Consistency
- Achieved a 94% increase in resolving production issues and 75% boost in software resiliency through a dedicated monitoring team and
- Implemented Scrum and directed four teams with a 97% success rate on commitments, including a ten-month streak of 100% successful deployments and software acceptance by stakeholders
- Enhanced work refinement 50% by establishing architecture standards, including UML reference architecture for technologies like .NET Core, Swift/Kotlin, Azure IaC, and VueJS
- Migrated 15 .NET, iOS, and Android build pipelines to Azure DevOps and Visual Studio App Center from physical Mac Mini, manual processes, and BitBucket pipelines
- Reduced basic tech service costs by \$5000/month using DocFx and Microsoft services through Office 365

Senior Manager, Product Development

Cincinnati, OH

Paycor

02/2019 - 08/2019

Engineered transformative enhancements for the identity and portal services engineering teams at a leading HR software company, resulting in a 30% reduction in vulnerabilities

- Improved monthly release model with Semantic Versioning, Shift Left testing, and Polly resilience that resulted in 100% success rate over six months and 25% work item acceptance rate, providing confidence for stakeholders
- Managed 3 engineering teams totaling 18 direct reports, overseeing portal services and identity management used by all software teams

Experience

IT Manager and Lead Developer **CBTS**

Cincinnati, OH

07/2015 - 01/2019

Orchestrated the transition of clients to a new enterprise development practice, integrating Agile & Scrum methodologies and boosting software delivery speed by 40% while achieving a 15% increase in client satisfaction

- Partnered with the sales team to serve as solution architect on RFPs, estimates, and presentations for 10 new client engagements
- Led managerial/HR functions for diverse teams, executing performance reviews, resolving intricate conflicts, and streamlining onboarding for 50+ new hires
- Stabilized client software delivery by 85% with a proper Scrum model, implementing new Gitflow source control management and Microsoft Architecture Guidance
- Created 30 automated pipelines for 6 clients using new Azure IaaS/PaaS/SaaS infrastructure for all QA testing and CI/CD releases

Team Lead and Principal Consultant

Cincinnati, OH

Cardinal Solutions

03/2012 - 07/2015

Led company standards, recommended architecture, and four person engineering team at a consultant company specializing in SharePoint and .NET projects

- · Created an in-house software framework used in all SharePoint projects that enabled developers to rapidly create new projects for clients and for other developers to contribute with 92% less time for project onboarding
- Performed comprehensive requirements gathering, project estimation, and statement of work for clients and worked with client cross functional teams to deliver transformative recommendations for SharePoint and .NET projects
- Conducted new technology training in the corporate office and other national branches for 100+ developers, covering JavaScript, jQuery, SharePoint CSOM

Skills

Strategic Software Planning · Technical Strategy · Agile & Scrum Methodologies · Risk Management · On & Offshore Management · Customer Service · Advocating Change · Servant Leadership · Career Development · .NET Development · Microservices · Angular · Docker & Kubernetes · Azure · SDLC

Achievements



Barry-Wehmiller Leadership Award Leadership award that recognizes team members whose thoughts, words, and action embody the tenets of people centric leadership



Microsoft TEALS Program

Volunteered in computer science courses at Jennings School District (MO) with an emphasis on programming languages, advising course materials, and evaluating assignments



NKU Informatics Program

Volunteered as part of the Government, Corporate and Foundation Engagement (GCFE) in the College of Informatics; evaluated student projects and presented real life scenarios, and real projects as examples

Education

University of Missouri - Saint Louis Computer Science and Mathematics

St. Louis, MO